Dmitrii Novikov, Senior Software Engineer

7nolikov@gmail.com LinkedIn, GitHub

Summary

- Senior Software Engineer with over **5 years** of experience in backend development (**Java, Spring Boot**) within the retail, telecommunications, and e-commerce business domains and **3 years** of QA Engineer background.
- Experience in **Google Cloud** and **Kubernetes** environments and maintaining a **cloud-native** data platform.
- Accelerated **twice** a paperless process for sales, significantly reducing operational costs and increasing income across the **20,000** branches company network by integrating QR code scanning technology.
- Bachelor's degree in **Computer Science**.

Skills

Programming and Development: Java (Spring Framework, Spring Boot, Spring Data, Spring Test), SQL & NoSQL Databases (PostgreSQL, MongoDB), RESTful APIs, GraphQL, Microservices Architecture, Cloud-native Development **Cloud Technologies & DevOps:** Google Cloud Platform (GCP, GKE, Anthos, App Engine, IAM, Datastore, Pubsub, Cloud Storage, Cloud Run), Containerization and Orchestration (Docker, Kubernetes), Continuous Integration/Continuous Deployment (CI/CD) using GitLab CI

Testing & Version Control: Unit Testing & Integration Testing (JUnit, Mockito), API Testing (Postman), Git **Additional Tools and Technologies:** Keycloak, Redis, RabbitMQ, Minio, Build Tools (Maven, Gradle)

Professional Experience

EPAM Systems April 2019 – Present

EPAM is a global leader in digital transformation and product development, included in the S&P 500 and the top 15 IT companies on the Fortune 1000.

Senior Software Engineer | EPAM Systems, Herceg Novi, Montenegro

June 2022 – Present

Project: Open source, standards-based, **cloud-native** platform for managing and analyzing data in real-time for the oil and gas industry. The project was a highly scalable and fault-tolerant system consisting of more than 20 microservices, and it provided a comprehensive set of services for managing and analyzing data in real-time.

- Advanced the capabilities of an oil and gas industry cloud-native data platform by successfully integrating an
 on-premise solution with an existing Google Cloud-based system consisting of more than 20 interconnected
 microservices. This integration involved bare Kubernetes and introducing PostgreSQL and Minio drivers to
 enhance operational flexibility for the client's hybrid cloud and on-premise environments.
- Enhanced software observability for improved troubleshooting and debugging by introducing an 'info' endpoint that dynamically collects build and version details of dependent services such as Java microservices, Redis, and Elastic, using Spring Boot's auto-configuration feature.
- Significantly enhancing system portability and flexibility while minimizing vendor lock-in risks by implementing a **cloud-agnostic storage layer**. This achievement involved integrating a **multi-cloud drivers** library that enabled seamless compatibility with various storage types.

Software Engineer | EPAM Systems, Saratov, Russian Federation

April 2019 – June 2022

Project: Legacy stores backend platform for a top retail company to handle a high volume of transactions, support a variety of payment methods, and be integrated with other systems such as inventory management and CRM systems.

- Accelerated twice the process for sales, significantly reducing operational costs and increasing income across the 20,000 branches company network by integrating QR code technology and reducing the amount of scanning.
- Saved approximately **80 hours per week** of manual data input work previously performed by staff members by introducing a pick-list generating service and hotkeys for popular categories at self-service checkout.
- Significantly decreased the average service time per customer and reduced the cost of receipt tape across the entire retail network by implementing a paperless process for check returning using QR code scanning and the option to disable printing of canceled receipts.

Software Engineer | Grid Dynamics, Saratov, Russian Federation

August 2018 – April 2019

Grid Dynamics is a NASDAQ publicly traded leader in enterprise digital transformation services for Fortune 1000 corporations.

Project: Internal employees' business trips and relocation tracking platform.

- Dramatically cut travel request processing time by **50%** through the development of a tracking solution utilizing Java, Spring Boot, and PostgreSQL.
- Boosted the accuracy of travel expense reporting by 20% by implementing a comprehensive suite of integration API and UI tests. This ensured seamless interoperability of the platform's services, which was achieved using tools like Spring Test, OpenFeign, and Selenium.

Kotlin Software Engineer | DeliverAI, Freelance project

December 2017 – August 2018

DeliverAI is a cloud-based online ordering and delivery management platform that helps businesses sell their products and services online and manage their delivery operations.

Project: Food delivery platform that connects customers with restaurants and stores for convenient and fast delivery.

- Designed and developed an MVP of the delivery marketplace platform from scratch to the first release.
- Led a **small team** of freelancers, providing mentorship and guidance using pair programming and code review practices.
- Worked closely with stakeholders to understand their needs and ensure the MVP met their expectations. Held regular **demonstrations** with stakeholders to get feedback and adjust the product as needed.

QA Engineer | **Terralink**, *Moscow*, *Russian Federation*

March 2017 – December 2017

TerraLink - one of the leading international system integrators, occupies a leading position in the information technology market in Russia and the CIS countries. More than 700 engineers work for the company worldwide.

• Contributed to TerraLink product integration for a leading mobile operator in Russia by working together with business analysts **onsite** and providing **defect analysis** reports and statistics.

QA Engineer | Netcracker Technology, Saratov, Russian Federation

June 2015 – March 2017

NetCracker is the largest software and IT services and solutions provider for telecommunications companies worldwide. More than 7,000 engineers work for the company worldwide.

- Successfully integrated the NetCracker product for 5 different clients by working as a Quality Assurance Engineer.
- Provided comprehensive defect analysis, contributing to improved product performance and customer satisfaction.
- Led the **onboarding process** for new team members, focusing on the NetCracker product and its integration process.
- Significantly reduced time and cost of testing while improving accuracy and reliability through the implementation of an **automated testing** framework for regression and smoke scopes.

Education

Saratov State University named after N.G.Chernyshevsky, Saratov, Russian Federation
Bachelor's degree, Information Technology

June 2017